Guide to the John Ruskin Letters to Ellen Heaton
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Letters from John Ruskin to Ellen Heaton, Ruskin, John, 1819-1900
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October or November; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.42)
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Aldborough, Suffolk; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Alnwick Castle, Northumberland; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Folkestone from the Sea; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October or November; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.43)
    "I hope to call in Salisbury place on Saturday at one, or thereabouts -- meantime, if you can offer White 170 cash for Alnwick tomorrow, I think he is sure to take it. If he won't take the Alborough [sic] -- which is on the whole the most valuable drawing, but the Alnwick is the most exchangeable one on the market, in case you tire of it." [Date provided by Surtees: October - November 1856]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Alnwick Castle, Northumberland; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; White, David Thomas; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October or November; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.44)
    "I have only offered 150 guineas for the Alborough [sic] alone, after thinking well over the matter. You will hear on Monday if accepted. I will tell you more, when I see you." [Date provided by Surtees: October - November 1856]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Aldborough, Suffolk; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October or November; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.45)
    "I really am not such a wretch as I seem to be -- I do want to see you & thank you very much & hear about poor Mr Richmond -- but I have been shaky and breakdownish this last week -- obliged to be idle & think of nothing. Can you come out here to lunch & for a quiet talk on Thursday next -- about ½ past one? if not -- I will come & see you instead -- but come if you can." [Date provided by Surtees: October - November 1856]
    Richmond, Thomas, 1802-1874; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October or November; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.46)
    Ruskin advises Heaton to purchase Turner's Aldborough as soon as is possible and requests that she send the money and makes the arrangements with the dealer [White] as much as she can without him as Ruskin doesn't "like any direct dealings with White just now.". Ruskin tells Heaton that if she can provide more money in cash, White would likely sell her a vignette of Walter Scott's house. Ruskin ends by saying he hopes he can meet with Heaton on Thursday. [Date provided by Surtees: October - November 1856]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Aldborough, Suffolk; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; White, David Thomas; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October or November; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.47)
    "Tomorrow -- 12, just the thing: -- we shall have a quiet hour -- at any rate. I fear I shall be interrupted at ½ past two -- but I have no better day. -- It really looks as if I did'nt care about the Dante, not to have come for it -- but I could'nt. I shall be so much obliged if you will bring it -- always faithfully Yrs." [Date provided by Surtees: Wednesday (October - November 1856)]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 November; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.48)
    "All's quite right. The Scott's house goes to a noble fellow [Charles Eliot Norton] to whom it will be very useful & Corinth is yours if you like to have it when I like to give it to you! which won't be for some time yet. I enjoy your picture so much." [Date provided by Surtees: November 1856]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Corinth from the Acropolis; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Norton, Charles Eliot, 1827-1908; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 late November; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.49)
    Ruskin advises Heaton on the preservation of her recently acquired Turner pieces, stating that the Walls of Rome and St Angelo can be displayed, provided they are "securely pasted in at the back." He says that he would not expose the Parnassus at all, for fear of damage by gas. He tells Heaton that candlelight would not damage the works. Turner praises Elizabeth Barrett Browning's Aurora Leigh as the "finest [poem] in the English language." He has lost the Brownings' Florence address and asks Heaton to send it to him. Ruskin exclaims: "NO CHALK from anybody" and says he will look at some Maddox Brown water colours and tell Heaton about them - he is not quite sure about them at the present moment. In a postscript, Ruskin tells Heaton she doesn't need to be as careful with Turner's Aldborough which is "not one half so delicate as the vignettes.". [Date provided by Surtees: End of November 1856]
    Painting -- Conservation and restoration; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Aldborough, Suffolk; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Castle of St Angelo; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Walls of Rome with the Tomb of Caius Sestus; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Parnassus and Castalian Spring; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Brown, Ford Madox, 1821-1893; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 late November; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 12 x 18 cm (Box 1, Folder H.50)
    "Don't send Parnassus. Gas is poison to pictures & drawings." [Date provided by Surtees: Probably end of November 1856]
    Painting -- Conservation and restoration; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Parnassus and Castalian Spring; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 December 13; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 32 x 21 cm (Box 1, Folder H.51)
    Ruskin tells Heaton that he has been enjoying Turner's Aldborough at a viewing by Thomas Richmond. He remarks: "it is most beautiful and it gives [him] intense pleasure to have it a little while by [him]." Ruskin gives Heaton the dates for her vignettes (1832 and 1833), stating that the drawings date from about a year earlier. Ruskin comments that they "are characteristic of Turners late middle period when everybody was already mocking & laughing at him." He says that Turner's "blazing" Ulysses & Polyphemus was exhibited in the Royal Academy in 1829. In a postscript, Ruskin claims he can't quite pinpoint the weakness in Heaton's writing but that if she reads Bunyan, Bacon and Helps, she will "feel it." He agrees to mark some passages for her. He admits that he has been so dazzled by Elizabeth Browning's work, he doesn't "feel able to describe or say anything, myself.".
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Aldborough, Suffolk; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Ulysses deriding Polyphemus; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Richmond, Thomas, 1802-1874; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 January 11; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 sheets; 1 folded (5 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm and 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.52)
    Ruskin tells Heaton she is most tolerant person he knows. He goes on to advise her on her writing style, suggesting she makes her use of pronouns consistent, better utilizes the active voice and makes her sentences more concise. He objects to her anthropomorphization of animals and the weather. He advises Heaton to make her caterpillar "full of Caterpillar faults - like a poor mortal" and suggests she change the caterpillar's characterization. Ruskin says he hasn't acquired her Venice photos yet but that he will be able to now that he has finished "something" [Notes on the Turner Gallery at Marlborough House, 1856]. He ends by saying that her Turner piece, Aldborough, is "a trump of a drawing" and that she "will never tire of it, it's glorious.".
    Rhetoric; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Aldborough, Suffolk; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, January 1857; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.54)
    Ruskin tells Heaton he does not have any works by William Holman Hunt and advises her to get as many Turners as possible while they are on the market, although he won't let her have his Corinth. He tells Heaton that they will rise in value and that he is "buying all I can afford" suggesting that she can "help Pre Rs after present opportunities are gone for Turner." He gives Heaton further advice on her writing. Ruskin gives Heaton prices at which he can acquire works by Turner for her and says he can recommend one for her, if Heaton can afford it. [Date provided by Surtees: January 1857]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Corinth from the Acropolis; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Hunt, William Holman, 1827-1910; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 January 20?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.55)
    Ruskin tells Heaton he will send her the drawings on Monday. He has bought her two drawings by Turner, at £95. He asks if she could pay him the money by Tuesday morning. He describes the works' dimensions and subject matter ("studies from nature") and says that "they will be nearly unique out of the national collection.". [Date provided by Surtees: ? Tuesday, 20 January 1857]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 January 22; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.56)
    Ruskin begins by asking Heaton for a further £5. He says he will not send her recently purchases vignettes by railroad "because they are wholly unreplaceable" but says that he will send the sketch, once it is insured. He tells Heaton that he is negotiating to change one of the pieces "the golden grey, for a blue one" which he thinks she will like better. In a postscript, he tells Heaton not to try to secure Rossetti's appearance at the Manchester Art Treasures Exhibition as Ruskin is trying to get him to stand for election to the Water-colour Society, where Heaton can display her Rossetti alongside Ruskin's Beatrice. Ruskin says that £84 more is all he will ask Heaton to spend this year. [Date provided by Surtees: Thursday, January 22nd 1857]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Art Treasures Exhibition ( 1857 Manchester, England); Old Water-Colour Society (London, England); Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 January 24; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.57)
    Ruskin tells Heaton it is too wet to send her drawings today. Ruskin has negotiated a vignette for Heaton at 40 guineas and two sketches at "55 each", a little more than Ruskin had expected. Ruskin says he will send a letter with a full account of the negotiations, which he has not posted so as "not to take up [Heaton's] head with business on Sunday.". Ruskin says that if Heaton tells him whether she's going to take the vignette, the drawings will arrive on Tuesday. [Date provided by Surtees: Saturday [January 24th 1857]
    Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 January 24; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 sheets (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 32 x 20 cm; 32 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder H.58)
    This letter outlines Ruskin's negotiations for two sketches and a vignette, all by Turner, on Heaton's behalf. He begins by reiterating that it is too wet to send the works to her today. Ruskin goes into to great detail about the course of the negotiations. Ruskin ends by praising Turner's Calais depictions and gives Heaton further advice on preserving, mounting and exhibiting the works in her collection. Ruskin details the price for the three works and asks Heaton to let him know as soon as possible whether she would like to take them.
    Painting -- Conservation and restoration; Picture frames and framing; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 January 26; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.59)
    "Alls safe. I have the ½ notes and you shall have no yellows or browns, but scarlet and blue -- or golden grey.-- I haven't yet dispatch'd the things because I have not yet decided on choice between two -- it will be settled today & fairly off tomorrow." [Date provided by Surtees: Monday, January 26th 1857]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 January 27; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.60)
    "I despatch [sic] today by fast train, the folio with two sketches & vignettes. If you are at all disappointed at first, with the first, remember what value attaches to them as what Turner did for his own delight in his best time; All the finished drawings were more or less got up -- the subjects forced on him by public or publisher. But these two records of his evening walk on Calais sands were done for his own delight before he went to bed -- for nobody to see but himself." [Date provided by Surtees: Tuesday, (January 27th 1857)]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 January 28; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.61)
    "My dear Ellen, I'm tired of writing Miss H; & as I've two or three lady correspondents who let me use their Xtrian names I dare say you will too -- I hope you have got all safe. The plan of keeping vignettes for exchange is just right ... I was only afraid you might be put to inconvenience for the money or I should have advised this at once -- I have the half notes all right." [Date provided by Surtees: Wednesday, January 28th 1857]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 January 29; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.62)
    Ruskin confirms he has received Heaton's notes and says he is glad that she is less disappointed with the sketches than she is with the vignette as "the former are first-rate -- the latter second rate." He admits that the vignette's sky is "very fine" and praises Turner's use of light and representation of storm clouds. He remarks to Heaton that she has "been spoiled by having those toppers of vignettes first" and that he "grudged [her] that Lochmaben exceedingly." Ruskin asks Heaton to find out the story behind the Lochmaben and the identity of the "lady being stabbed.". Ruskin knows of a Lochmaben ballad about a stolen mare but states that it is not the tale represented in the Turner work. Ruskin ends: "Great purchase not concluded yet -- You shall hear soon." [Date provided by Surtees: Thursday, January 29th 1857]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 January 31; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.63)
    "Great purchase is going on: but not settled yet. It may involve various sacrifices on my part and among others, that of my beautiful Rossetti. Supposing I were obliged to let it go -- would you like to have it at 40[...]?[...]I hope you will not find your Turner sketches quite so unacceptable to the multitude as you seem to think. I consider the one with the children quite a drawing. I will most certainly relieve you of them in a little while if you don't like them." In a postscript Ruskin lists the following works as those he is hoping to acquire in the "great purchase": Melrose (frontispiece), Coriskin (frontispiece) and Fort Augustus (title-page) from Walter Scott's works; Turner's Rouen from St. Catherine's Hill and Dinant. [Date provided by Surtees: Saturday (January 31st 1857)]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 February 2; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.64)
    Ruskin approves that Heaton proposes to continue acquiring Turners, for the moment. Ruskin says he has never used Heaton's money for personal gain but concedes that Heaton's brother has grounds to suspect Ruskin might be leading her "astray" in her purchases, not being assured of the value of the Turners and Rossettis. Ruskin says it is unlikely that he will have to sell his Rossetti and that he wouldn't want to prevent Heaton from purchasing other works by convincing her to buy the Rossetti. He tells Heaton he has secured the Turner works in the "great purchase" but that the Scotts are still in question, as the owner will not agree to sell them. Ruskin asks Heaton if she has engravings from Turner's Rivers of France series. He sketches one of the works from the series saying "it is this Rouen and I'm in such a state of excitement I don't know what to do." [Date provided by Surtees: Probably Monday, February 2nd 1857]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 February 4?; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.65)
    "What a capital worker you are. Best thanks. But we must find out what that old vagabond of a Turner meant by that bit of brown assassination [ Lochmaben Harper vignette]." In a postscript, "I was excited merely by securing and having always near me that drawing [the Rouen referred to in his previous letter to Heaton]." [Date provided by Surtees: Wednesday ? February 4th 1857]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 early February; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.66)
    Ruskin tells Heaton he is uncomfortable with her having purchased "those two Calais's", as he finds the subjects of the works very similar. Ruskin proclaims "the one with the posts" "magnificent" and worth at least 100 guineas but admits that the more he reflected on the other, the less he liked it. Ruskin tells Heaton if she sends him £26.10 he can exchange the second for two drawings on blue paper, one of Ehrenbreitstein and one of Genoa. Ruskin says that drawings on blue paper are rare and that, if Heaton allowed him to make an engraving from the Ehrenbreitstein, it would double its value. Ruskin says if she agrees to the exchange, she must send the Calais by the next post or (if the next post is near) by the post after that. Heaton may send the money "at [her] leisure." Ruskin draws a line across the page, moving from A to B, stating that the width of the drawings is an inch broader than the line [the line measures 3.25 x 4.6 in., suggesting the drawings measure around 3.25 x 5.6 in.]. Ruskin notes that the drawings are worth 40 guineas each. [Date provided by Surtees: First half of February 1857]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 February 16; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.67)
    Ruskin opens by saying he is going to ask Heaton to help him "in a way which may at first be a little disagreeable to yourself - at least I hope so!" He explains that he has been asked to catologue, "or do what [he] liked in arrangement of the hundred [he was] to frame", all the Turner sketches in the National Gallery. He says he does not want his "enemies" to criticize him for sending Turner sketches to Heaton and so he will not be sending the sketches. He also asks Heaton to send him her "beautiful Calais posts.". He claims that, in return, he will procure finished works for her. In a postscript, Ruskin apologizes for the hastiness of the letter writing and gives Heaton instructions on how to send and package the work for sending.
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 late February; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.68)
    Ruskin tells Heaton he has received the money for the drawings and expresses his regret that he cannot send them straight away, assuring Heaton that they will not be sold to anyone else. Ruskin says that the Turner sketches may be sent back to her if "the whole course of negotiation between Mr Griffith & his French employer" becomes apparent. However, Ruskin is unsure "what is likely to come of them" because he does not know to whom they previously belonged. Ruskin says he expects Heaton's Calais to arrive that day. In a postscript, Ruskin admits that the "scruple" [presumably between Griffith and his employer] was originated by Ruskin's father and appeals to Heaton, saying: "[Ruskin] would not have acted by [Heaton] in this ungenerous way unless [he] was forced." [Date provided by Surtees: Latter half of February 1857]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Aldborough, Suffolk; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Griffith, Thomas, active 1831-1869; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 late February; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.69)